So now that we have seen how paging and
virtual to physical translation works,
let's talk about the memory access time
when we have this translation. So our
program does something like this. It
says load R1 from the address computed
by adding four to what is in R2. This
when computed will be the virtual
address that we want to access in the
program. So to do a load or restore, the
processor has to compute the virtual
address. This is quick. Usually it's
just addition of two numbers that are
already in the processor. One is a
constant fetch with the instruction. The
other one is the register that is inside
the processor. Next, the processor has
to compute the page number which is
extremely quick because it just means
that we take some bits from the virtual
address and without any address
translation. The next thing that the
processor will do is access the cache
and sometimes if there is a cache miss
the actual memory. So again these two
are extremely quick. Most of the time
will be spent accessing the cache and
occasionally we will spend more cycles
because we need to access the memory
with virtual to physical translation.
After computing the page number the
processor has to compute the physical
address of the page table entry where
the translation for the page number is.
This is done by adding the page number
that we computed to the beginning
address of the page table. Then we read
the actual page table entry and compute
the physical address by combining the
physical frame number from the page
table entry with the page offset from
the virtual address. So how fast is
this? Well, this is fast because it just
means adding the page number to some
sort of address. This is fast because it
only means combining two numbers that we
already have. But how fast is this? And
for that we need to ask ourselves so
where is the page table? Is it inside
the processor so it can be quickly
accessed or is it in memory? We have
seen that the page table can be fairly
large. Yes, for a multi-level page table
we can have it be less than a megabyte
for some programs but in theory it can
be extremely large. So we cannot
guarantee that the page table for even
one process fits on the processor chip
which means that the page tables really
need to be in memory. And that means
that for each load or store, we now need
to have a memory access, which is just
as slow as when we had a cache miss that
we were trying to avoid before we got to
page tables. Things are even worse
because for a multi-level page table,
for example, a four-level page table, we
would need to do this multiple times.
For example, four times. Compute the
physical address of the outermost page
table. Read that entry. Compute the
physical address of the next page table.
Go ahead and do that four times. So we
need four memory accesses to read the
four page table entries until we get the
actual translation after which we can
quickly access the cache. So somehow we
have a situation where the virtual to
physical address translation is costing
us more than the memory accesses that we
try to avoid by having the caches.